A Guide to the Theodore Dreiser Collection, 1917-1937
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Theodore Dreiser Collection, 1917-1937
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6220-h
This collection consists of 23 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Contents List
- Letters
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to [Ralph H.] Holmes, The Times, Detroit, Michigan 1917 Dec 24, ALS, 3 p.
    Thanks him for clippings, letter; offers to print them; mentions essay, Dreiser's role as reporter; other clippings.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ralph H. Holmes, Detroit 1918 Nov 14, ALS, 1 p.
    Writes that he will be glad to see him again; asks him to call; promises to find telephone list.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Los Angeles, to Ralph H. Holmes 1920 Apr 25, ALS, 2 p.
    Thanks him for 4 clippings; asserts that clipping services rarely do better than 30% on notices; believes examinations of book will be interesting; mentions book, possibility of leaving New York for the summer.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Ralph H. Holmes 1926 Mar 3, ALS, 1 p.
    Thanks him for note and clipping; smiles at him bawling out loud in the silence of his room; sympathizes with humane response; mentions moving the hardened newspaperman and critic.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ralph H. Holmes, Detroit 1929 Feb 15, TLS, 1 p.
    [Includes autograph and postscript; mentions Kraft, possible dramatization of Sister Carrie, John Howard Lawson, Pantomime Ballet in Detroit; committee of 100 to invite Soviet Ballet to America; asks what Detroit names he needs.]
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ralph H. Holmes, Detroit 1929 Feb 25, TLS, 2 p.
    Discusses plan to bring Russian ballet company to America; mentions Otto Kahn's donation of $25,000, assistance of Donald Freeman and Frank Crowishield; encloses copy of proposal for corporation to control money and movements of the tour; declines presidency of company; asks him to approach donors in Detroit; discusses Russian government and publicity of tour.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Ralph H. Holmes 1929 Feb 26, ALS, 1 p.
    Thinks he should have these, but no publicity should happen yet.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Ralph H. Holmes 1929 Mar 21, ALS, 2 p.
    Thanks him for tips; mentions sending someone to Detroit, musical director, engagements in Detroit, Cleveland, and Buffalo; encloses letters showing how things stand financially; writes that $100,000 has been pledged; intends to let him know when Russian authoritative news is released.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ralph H. Holmes, Detroit 1929 May 13, TLS, 1 p.
    Thanks him for outline of proposed dramatization of Sister Carrie; likes idea of 2 stages; believes a producer other than Kraft will undertake the project; thanks him for comments on An American Tragedy trial; believes Massachusetts law is likely to be changed.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ralph H. Holmes 1929 Jul 31, Telegram, 1 p.
    Discusses contract with Leah Salisbury, which he has not signed; asks him to straighten her out.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ralph H. Holmes, Detroit 1929 Aug 17, TLS, 1 p.
    Plans to grant him 4 months exclusive dramatizing privilege from August 1 December 1, 1929; plans to extend his share of 45% of American stage royalties and 1/6 of all screen and talkie rights to English speaking countries; wishes to retain rights in foreign language field; mentions case of Sister Carrie.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Ralph H. Holmes 1930 Feb 10, ALS, 2 p.
    Believes Sister Carrie manuscript has possibilities, except for scene 5, which is hopeless; mentions Hurstwood, antique Broadway machinery, lighting, sequence of scenes, and photographs of house.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Ralph H. Holmes 1930 Mar 5, TLS, 1 p.
    Writes that 4 people have examined Sister Carrie manuscript; lists that 2 stage idea is not good, the play is 3 hours long, and other criticisms; believes he is already committed to Miss Salisbury and cannot let Elizabeth Marbury have a hand in production of Sister Carrie; asks him to talk to Marbury because she believes play will fail in present form.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Tuscon, to Ralph H. Holmes, Detroit 1930 Mar 28, ALS, 2 p.
    Writes that bronchitis drove him to Tuscon; awaits revised version; hopes to be back in New York in May; thanks him for enclosed snapshot of Dreiser.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Ralph H. Holmes 1930 Jul 29, ALS, 2 p.
    Sends manuscripts for Sister Carrie, apart from last version which is with Elizabeth Marbury; thinks last 3-4 pages should be doctored, as ending is very important; mentions several producers.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Ralph H. Holmes 1930 Aug 23, TLS, 1 p.
    Plans to see Laringer if he is in city and presents himself; reports Elizabeth Marbury has consulted producers and response is adverse; relates her criticisms, which he intends to send a copy of some day.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Mt. Kisco, New York, to Ralph H. Holmes, Detroit 1932 Oct 4, TLS, 1 p.
    Encloses slip and publisher's announcement to explain [ The American Spectator], edited by George Jean Nathan, Ernest Boyd, James Branch Cabell, and himself; discusses editorial goals, monthly payment of $.01 a word with 1500 words as maximum and 500 as minimum; offers to convince others if he get s document that convinces him.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Mt. Kisco, New York, to Ralph H. Holmes, Detroit 1935 Nov 26, TLS, 1 p.
    Thanks him for letter; expresses pleasure in doing something for Tobacco Road; plans to be in Mt. Kisco through winter.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Mt. Kisco, to Ralph H. Holmes, Detroit 1936 Sep 18, TLS, 1 p.
    Writes that he tried to get in touch with him, but could not find him; hopes not to miss him in New York.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ralph H. Holmes, Detroit 1937 Oct 14, ALS, 1 p.
    Plans to be in New York for time being; gives time he will be available.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ralph H. Holmes, Detroit 1937 Nov 1, TLS, 1 p.
    Acknowledges receipt of telegram; writes that he called hotel and would like to have seen him to go over various matters; asks when he can find him.
- Miscellaneous
  - Advertising circular for play, The Hand of the Potterca. 1919, Circular
    Gives history of the four-act tragedy; includes reviews pro and con.
  - Clipping of 5 poems from New York Evening Post Literary Review1924 Dec 20, Clipping
    Includes: "The Tower," "The Poet," "In a Country Graveyard," "The Hidden God," and "A New Day."